<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the thirteenth of Iune, the second Sunday in trinitie tearme 1591 by Thomas Barne ...</title>
            <author>Barne, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1464.8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22143985</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22143985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1762:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the thirteenth of Iune, the second Sunday in trinitie tearme 1591 by Thomas Barne ...</title>
                  <author>Barne, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacking all after signature D4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 2nd, II, 1-3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT PAVLS CROSSE THE THIRTEENTH OF IVNE, THE SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſunday in Trinitie tearme 1591. by THOMAS BARNE <hi>ſtudent in Diuinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Brethren I exhort you to watch thoſe that make diuiſions and offences among you, and decline from them. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Cap.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Fruſtra autem (vt ait quidam) niti, ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nihil aliud litigando niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dium quaerere extremae dementiae eſt. <bibl>Hieronymus ad Domnionem &amp; Rogatianum.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Nullum vitium eſt quod non à mendacio ſumit originem ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> virtus cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius non ſit origo veritas. <bibl>Ioannes Maxentius aduerſus epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum Ormiſdae.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <q>ACADEMIA OXONIENSI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritas in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <p>JOSEPH <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by IOSEPH BARNES, Printer to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie.</hi> 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL GEORGE RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERHAM ESQVIER, HIGH SHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of Bedforde-ſhiere: THOMAS BARNE <hi>wiſheth peace and prosperity in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> PRESENT vnto your worſhip a copy of that Sermon, the which I preached pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely at Pauls Croſſe: in that I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perſuaded, that the doctrine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteined, is requiſite and expedient for theſe daies. The which when I had conſidered, I found ſundry and diuerſe men that had cloathed themſelues in Phariſaicall garments, wherein was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodered the ſumme of Chriſtianity, they themſelues in the meane ſeaſon altogether depriued of the grace of God. <hi>Faith</hi> ſaieth the Apoſtle, <hi>it is the gift of God, and in vaine tendeth all our preaching, if the heart and ſoule of man bee not prepared before by the speciall aſsiſtance of Gods spirit: Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollo</hi> may water, but if God doeth not giue the encreaſe all tendeth to ſmall effect.</p>
            <p>The Virgins that ſlept, and had not their lamps burning, were forthwith excluded the preſence of the Bridegroome. The figtree, that had broade and greene leaues, and no fruite, once curſed, withered. So it falleth out with vs, which in externall ſhew attend and expect the comming of the ſonne of man, are found at the laſt vnfit to attend vpon him, although wee make glorious ſhewes of Chriſtianity, and doe not perfourme works of charity. Theſe and ſuch like maladies haue infected diuers, the which of a zeale haue put forth themſelues before they were called, and in a vaine preſumption of humane learning, haue
<pb facs="tcp:25165:3"/> cauſed the weaker ſort to follow them, and to relie vpon them, that were not able to upholde themſelues. Such men were <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomius, Vigilantius,</hi> whom <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> in his ſecond booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>quaeſtiones in Exodum,</hi> tearmeth <hi>opicos mures</hi> the which are <hi>spumei in ſermrne &amp; in fide parum ſani:</hi> of whom <hi>Saint Cyprian</hi> in his booke <hi>de ſimplicitate praelotorum</hi> ſpeaketh in this wiſe. <hi>Hi ſunt qui ſe vltro apud temerarios conuenas ſine diuina diuina dispoſitione praeficiunt, qui ſe praepoſitos ſine vlla ordinationis lege conſtituunt qui ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine epiſcopatum dante epiſcopi nomen aſſumunt.</hi> The which wordes of thir bleſſed and aged father duely conſidered, lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the prepoſterous courſe of ſundry leaders in theſe daies, the which exclame againſt <hi>Ceſar</hi> and his right labouring as much as lieth in them, to plucke vp by the rootes that which they neuer planted.</p>
            <p>So heady, that they wil not ſtand to the trueth receaued, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching contrarieties, of whom <hi>Irenaeus li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 15. ſpeaketh: <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp; Ptolomaeus deliri &amp; fanatici homines auditores ſuos, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictores fecerunt,</hi> as theſe can ſufficiently approue. This Sermon diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peruſed, laieth open the ſiniſter meanes, and deceitful practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe men, the which beeing vnſtable in their doctrine (as the ſundry change of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi>) approueth: haue at the laſt followed the ſteps of the <hi>Parmenian,</hi> to contempe all men in reſpect of themſelues, whom <hi>Optatus</hi> in his 2. booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Parme:</hi> counſelleth and aduiſeth in this wiſe. <hi>Non enim spiritum Dei ſoli vobis uindicare poteſtis aut includere quod intelligitur &amp; non videtur, per mitte deum vnde velit ire &amp; quo velit accedere, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat libertatem qui audiri poteſt videri non poteſt.</hi> A kingdome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in it ſelfe cannot ſtand, ſathan if hee were in armes againſt himſelfe, his kingdome forthwith would bee ended: diſcorde crept in among the Romans, &amp; ouerthrew the Roman Empire. The parts in mans body if they were at variance, life could not long continue ſaied <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi> long ago. And ſo, <hi>ſi paruis componere magna liceret,</hi> The Church of Chriſt cannot continue among vs, ſith one preacher ioyeth to contradict another: and delight in nouelties, and few to be found that dares oppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to withſtand theſe men, the which pretend conformity &amp; order, and practiſe nothing elſe but irregular diſorder. Let the Church or <hi>Scotland</hi> be diligently regarded: good God? What vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores and tumults hath that poore Ilande ſuſteined by factious
<pb facs="tcp:25165:3"/> and ſeditious means &amp; what hath it procured in the end but flat rebellion, ſuch malecontents among vs at home, haue as much as lieth in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſgraced the eſtabliſhed gouernment of our church as diuers books 15 years paſſed printed at <hi>Andwerp</hi> can ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie: &amp; theſe men to obtaine a name &amp; to enrich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues haue procured a defection from our Church: contemning the Right Reuerend fathers of our Church &amp; wilfully oppoſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt al lawful authority whatſoeuer. Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well bee reſembled to one <hi>Hermogenes</hi> of whom <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his booke the vvhich hee wrought againſt him reporteth that hee was <hi>homo in ſaeculo turbulentus, qui Loquacitatem facundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am exiſtimat, &amp; impudentiam conſtantiam deputat, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidicere ſingulis officium bonae conſtantia iudicat.</hi> Such innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Religion are and haue beene daungerous and when men are zealous in contention, then doeth God permit them to bee guided by their ovvne diſcretion, and then that is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued a verity the which the Philoſopher gaue out long agoe, <hi>vno abſurdo conceſſo mille ſequuntur,</hi> when a man hath once made a breach into an abſurdity, it is an eaſie matter to cauſe him to graunt al abſurdities and contradictions whatſoeuer. Theſe and the like inconueniences to auoide with the which this age of ours aboundeth, I haue ſet downe my ſermon as I deliuered the ſame at Pauls Croſſe, in the which I haue laied vpon the cauſes of this ſchiſme &amp; diſſenſion with the which our Churh of England is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered, and the means to remoue the ſame. But I am aſſured that I do <hi>ſurdis canere cantilena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſpecially that vtterly reiect the authority of our Church. And frame vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a kinde of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath altered the courſe of ours, deliuered vnto vs by our fathers, the verity whereof to approue where nothing elſe then if I ſhould <hi>lucente ſole lychnum accendere.</hi> For the parties I woulde if I might chuſe not meddle with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they ſtand not to any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful authority, if ſcripture be vrged, expounded by the vniforme conſent of Chriſt his Church, the interpretation is reiected, &amp; the reaſon is at hand, the Church was then by hereſie corrupted. If the Canons of generall councels be cited: for the peaceable and godly gouernment of our Church. The fathers that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liued did <hi>caecutire</hi> they had not ſo ſpecial aportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods ſpirit as they haue obiect vnto them the eſtate of the Church as it is now, ratified by inuincible authorities of ſcripture, confirmed by the ancient
<pb facs="tcp:25165:4"/> fathers heretofore, defended by the bleſſed hand of her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty againſt the greateſt Monarches in Europe at this day. <hi>Iam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> faces &amp; ſaxa volant furor arma miniſtrat.</hi> And theſe are the men of whom <hi>Saint Hierom</hi> ſpeaketh in his Commentaries vpon the 5. Chapter of <hi>Saint Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians. Qui ſemel fuerit furore ſuperatus, neceſſe eſt vt profiliat in clamorem, &amp; turbide fremens huc at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illuc in modum fluuij ventiletur &amp; dicat: O rerum iniquitas: O iniuſta Dei iudicia, &amp; catera quae ſolent loqui, qui per indignationis fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem, mentis iudicium per diderunt.</hi> Theſe men I leaue to their owne phantaſies, and commend this my ſermon vnto your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip vnto whom I acknowledge my ſelfe in dutie greatly bound deſiring God to bleſſe your worſhip with many happy and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous yeares in this world to the glory of God and your hartes deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Oxon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>The ſecond Epiſtle of S. Peter 2. Cap. 1.2.3. verſ.</bibl>
                  <p>There were falſe Prophets among the people: ſo likewiſe there ſhalbe falſe teachers among you, which ſhal bring in damnable hereſies denying the Lord that redeemed them, bringing vpon themſelues a speedy deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and many ſhall follow their riotouſneſſe, by whom the way of truth ſhall be blasphemed. And in couetouſneſſe with pleaſing wordes, they ſhall buy and ſell you, whoſe iudgement that was long agoe doeth not linger and their deſtruction doeth not ſlumber.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Church of God the which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Saint Paul</hi> termeth the piller and the foundation of trueth: is as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth vpon the 28. Pſalme, planted in the middeſt of thornes and briers, <hi>omnes amici &amp; nulli pacifici,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 8.</note> ſayeth <hi>Hierom</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Damaſus.</hi> The crow that retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, and the Doue that brought an Oliue branch were preſerued from the generall deluge by the arch of <hi>Noah.</hi> Chriſt and his Church are one, therefore inſeperable: Chriſt the head, we his members. One God, one faith, one baptiſme. Is Chriſt deuided? or haue we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued any prerogatiue, but by the Croſſe of Chriſt? <hi>Saint Paul</hi> gloried in this onely, that he was crucified to the world, and the world vnto him. In theſe perilous and dangerous daies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery peculiar phantaſie be it neuer ſo ridiculous once ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder hypocriſie is accounted piety, wherein likewiſe, <hi>quot auditores tot detractores,</hi> as many auditors, ſo many detractors, I haue thought it neceſſary, to ſtay them that are running head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to their owne perdition and if it may be to plucke them out of the fier that are already ſchorched, and to remoue all occaſion of ſchiſme and diſſenſion, that as God is a God of peace, ſo wee likewiſe may endeuour to obſerue the vnity of the ſpirit in the bonde of peace. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh vnto vs, telling vs, that in God there is no change or ſhadow of chaunge, and if God bee alwaies one and the ſame, we ought likewiſe to conforme our ſelues vnto him, and to ſtand faſt in that doctrine which we haue receiued. And not to be caried away, with euery blaſt of vaine doctrine. The Apoſtle <hi>Saint Peter</hi> in theſe three verſes propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:25165:5"/> vnto vs, three ſeuerall partes to be obſerued: The firſt a propheticall prediction of the future calamities incident vnto the Church of Chriſt by falſe teachers conteined in theſe words: There were falſe Prophetes among the people ſo likewiſe their ſhalbe falſe teachers among you. During the time of the lawe <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Mambres, Balam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Boſor</hi> with others ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Church of God: Phariſies and Saduces, <hi>Elymas</hi> &amp; <hi>Simon Magus, Alexander</hi> the copper ſmith, raiſed ſedition among them Since their time <hi>Dioſciorus, Iouinian, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilantius</hi> iſſued forth, and theſe with <hi>Arrius</hi> and <hi>Eunomius</hi> brake downe the heads of the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neard <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, corrupting the word of God and perverting the ſame. Falſe prophets there were among the people ſo likewiſe there ſhall be falſe teachers among you. The ſecond containeth in it a deſcription of them: They ſhall priuily bring in ſects, damnable ſects denying the Lord that redeemed them and ſhal bring vpon themſelues a ſudden deſtruction, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men ſhall followe their riotouſnes, the way of trueth ſhalbe blaſphemed by them, and to enrich themſelues, they ſhall buy and ſell you, according to their owne diſpoſition. The third is the rigorous and feareful iudgement of God that houereth ouer their heads <hi>ſeta equina</hi> by a twine thread co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in theſe words The iudgement of theſe men doeth not linger, and the ruine and deſtruction of them all doeth not ſlumber. You ſee beloued, the ſcope and final end of the apoſtle, his words are plaine &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt verified at this day in the eies and eares of you all: and the like euent, that campe vpon them wil alſo light vpon vs, in that we haue deuided the cote of Chriſt that had no ſeame, and haue dried vp the ointment of vnity that ranne downe vpon <hi>Aarons</hi> beard euen vnto the ſkert of his garment. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> perpending the ſtate of his time, proteſted plainely, that if hee ſhould labour to pleaſe men, he could not be a Diſciple of Chriſt. And I would to God that there were not ſome to be found among vs that will preach according to the direction of their auditory from whence haue ryſen diuiſions tending to the ſubuertion of Chriſtian faith and religion, And from this ſort of men the Apoſtle exhorteth euery one to depart. The harueſt approacheth the Maſter of the ground expecteth a good croppe: but the tempeſtuous blaſt of ſchiſme and diuiſion, hath ſhaken the blade that the corne is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and he that threſheth the ſame ſhall well perceiue his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:25165:5"/> to bee loſt. Men and brethren in this militarie expedition, let euery one be aduiſed, how, and in what order hee ſtandeth. He that is perſuaded that he is ſure of foot, may fal, he that ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth may forthwith ſtumble: but in humility, let euery one learne: for God reſiſteth the proude, and applieth himſelfe to the humble, and hath dealt mercifully with the poore in ſpirit, when the rich men of the world haue beene ſent empty away. The Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy cap.</hi> 4. <hi>The ſpirit speaketh plainely, that in the later daies certaine ſhall reuolt from the faith.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> addicting themſelues to ſpirits of errour,<note place="margin">Oecumenius in <hi>4.</hi> cap. epiſt. ad Timoth.</note> ſo <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenius</hi> ſpeaketh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That hee that hath once ſwarued from the verity of Gods word, is preſently caried awaie with euery fantaſie. In the infancy of the Church ſprang forth <hi>Cerinthus</hi> and <hi>Saturninus,</hi> in the ſecond centenarie iſſued forth <hi>Carpocrates</hi> and <hi>Montanus,</hi> in the third <hi>Nouatus</hi> and <hi>Sabellius,</hi> in the fourth, <hi>Eunomius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilantius,</hi> and <hi>Heluidius,</hi> in the fift <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> in the ſixt, <hi>Agnoitae, Monophyſitae,</hi> in the ſeuenth, <hi>Iacobitae</hi> and <hi>Sergius,</hi> that retchleſſe helhound, of whom <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſius Bibliothecarius</hi> maketh mention. And in theſe latter daies certaine ſhall reuolt from the faith, giuing attendance vnto ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of errour, and doctrine of deuils, as <hi>Palmerius</hi> did with <hi>Menno</hi> the Anababtiſt, denying the deity of the ſonne of God. As <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Ket</hi> did, not long ſince in <hi>Norwich,</hi> ſounding forth innouati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons contrary to the doctrine already receaued, with <hi>Browne</hi> and <hi>Barrow,</hi> making an externall ſhewe of piety, as the Puritanes in <hi>England</hi> doe at this day: diuiding themſelues from the Church of Chriſt, as withered branches, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tending <hi>de lanae caprina,</hi> for moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine in the water, haue among them a ſpotleſſe ſpouſe, as they tearme it, in the which there is no direct or preſcript forme of praier, but as the ſpirit miniſtreth, ſo euery one to ſpeake &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy. And theſe recuſants are planted in the ſuperlatiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, they are <hi>omnium infime,</hi> and yet <hi>ſuperbiſsimi,</hi> not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a bad cauſe by argument, exclaime againſt the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and her miniſters, and each of theſe is aſſured that he hath the ſpirit of God. Brethren whereſoeuer you be, and whoſoeuer you are, be not deceaued, for God aſſure your ſelues wil not be mocked. For a time he forbeareth but in his due time he ſtriketh: he is not tied or chained to any one corner of
<pb facs="tcp:25165:6"/> this land: his name is glorious in the middeſt of his people: there hath he planted an holy temple for himſelfe, an habitation for the God of <hi>Iacob.</hi> I pray you, looke into the practiſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the Church: I am a Prophet aſwell as you are, and my doctrine is deriued from heauen by reuelation. So thoſe ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Friers tearmed <hi>pauperes de Lugduno</hi> that roſe vp in the yeare a thouſand fiue hundreth and ſeuenty vnder <hi>Lucius</hi> the third and <hi>Alexander,</hi> the 3. Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> as writeth <hi>Abbas Vrspergenſis</hi> in the yeare a thouſand two hundreth and twelue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that they had a peculiar calling from God, and therefore they regarded not the ordinance of man. What was <hi>Samoſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Epiphanius</hi> in his ſecond booke <hi>contra haereſes</hi> reporteth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, puffed vp with a little learning that he had fell from the trueth. What cauſed <hi>Iulian</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Apoſtata to decline,<note place="margin">In Julianum oratio prima.</note> it was a <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of him, a preſumptuous opinion that he had of himſelfe, the which in the ende turned to his owne deſtruction. This ſelfe ſame thing <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth in his 53. tracte vpon <hi>Iohn: Quoſdam nimia ſuae voluntatis fiducia extulit in ſuperbiam, &amp; quoſdam nimia ſuae voluntatis diffidentia deiecit in negligentiam.</hi> Certaine there are ſaieth hee, that of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent opinion conceiued of themſelues, wax proude, and others diſtruſting themſelues, ſitte at home and doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And as <hi>Bernarde de conſideratione,</hi> to <hi>Eugenius, ocio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt, non tantum quia nihil operatur, ſed qui continuè laboran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do nihil tandem lucratur.</hi> That man ſaieth <hi>Bernarde,</hi> is not onelie ſaied to bee idle, that doeth nothing, but hee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that alvvaies turmoyleth, and reapeth nothing. So theſe zealous men caried awaie with a popular applauſe <hi>Saxum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant nitendo, nec proficiunt hylum:</hi> They are alwaies inueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the ſcandalous gouernement of our Church, and as <hi>Hierom</hi> vvriting to <hi>Marcellam</hi> ſpeaketh: <hi>Itur in verba: ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo teritur, lacerantur abſentes, vita aliena deſcribitur, &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes inuicem conſumimur ab inuicem.</hi> Here the quarrell beginneth, a diſputation is intended, and thereof procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth malice and rancour, and one enuying the other, one in the ende conſumeth another. Heretofore the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie was about <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, bookes extant at this day <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:25165:6"/> that right honourable, right reuerende, and moſt learned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church of <hi>Englande</hi> his grace of <hi>Canterburie</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently approued the ſame. The queſtion is now, whether our eccleſiaſticall order bee allowable by the word of God, and hereupon, as the Poet ſpeaketh <hi>ſucceſsit vetus comaedia &amp; in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium libertas excidit &amp; vim, dignam lege regi:</hi> for the liues of our ſpirituall fathers are made ſcandalous, their doctrine for faſhion ſake lightly regarded, and curſed cham <hi>Iohn Penrie</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> hath laied open the ſhame of his father, but a curſe ſhall light vpon his heade, his daies ſhall bee prolonged to his ovvne ſhame, and like a fugitiue hee ſhall begge his breade. A lewde liuer doeth not argue a corrupt teacher: Scribes and Phariſees were lewde liuers, and yet good prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and their doctrine ratyfied and approued by the ſonne of God. Chriſt was preached for enuy, hee that preached Chriſt in that order was a lewde liuer, yet a good preacher: <hi>Saint Paule</hi> gloried in him. Chriſt was preached for oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; hee that preached him in that order was a lewde li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, yet a good preacher, <hi>Saint Paule</hi> gloried in him. Bee the preacher in life laſciuious, if his doctrine bee good, <hi>Saint Paule</hi> ſpeaketh I haue reioyced in him, and I will reioyce. Men and brethren, I ſpeake not this to defende the irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar liues of anie, but onely to ſtoppe the mouthes of them that for a ſmall infirmitie vvoulde exclude the beſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in this lande from preaching, and beeing vnlearned la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to determine matters, the which they doe not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande. Although I wiſh daielie, that euery one of vs would conforme his life to his doctrine, for the vvorde and the woorke agreeing, doeth as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaketh in his Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the Prouerbes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it cauſeth the worde preached to bee better accepted. Falſe Prophets there were ſaieth the Apoſtle among the people, I haue not ſent them and they are gone: falſe Prophets are diſperſed among the people, ſo likewiſe there ſhall bee falſe teachers among you.<note place="margin">Hieronimus ad Fabiolam.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerued in his time three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſorts of falſe teachers, the worlde, the fleſh, and the deuill. The world maketh a great ſhewe of ſecurity, and in the ende it offereth vnto vs anguiſh and ſorrow. The fleſh
<pb facs="tcp:25165:7"/> aſſureth vnto vs continuall ioy, and ſudaine deſtruction is inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vnto her. The deuill, hee will not breake his promiſe, for honour and dignity are his rewards, and in them hee bringeth vs to perpetuall ſhame: <hi>ſic ſolet amicos beare ſuos,</hi> in this order doeth he magnifie himſelfe in his frends. In theſe daies wher hypocriſie can hardly be diſcerned from piety, it ſtandeth vs vpon to know a falſe teacher.<note place="margin">Hieron. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ad Iouinianum.</note> For as Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeaketh, <hi>O quantus eſt numerus falſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prophetarum in omni ſtatu, omnes viciſsim qui ex habitu ſuo, aut digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, aut officio, aut conditione praetendunt bonum &amp; faciunt malum, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes igitur habitum religionis deferentes, &amp; religionis opera non facientes.</hi> Falſe teachers, they ſwarme in euery corner, in euery place and age, men are apt enough to deceaue, and religion is nowe a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to graceleſſe and thriftleſſe men. The doctrine recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Church of God is not mutable, and the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is not mutable, ſo <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his booke <hi>de vera reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione cap.</hi> 53. affirmeth: The doctrine of our Puritanes it is muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, therefore it is not of God: <hi>Miſeri homines, &amp; miſerabiles quibus cognita vileſcunt, &amp; nouitatibus gaudent:</hi> they are ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the miſerableſt men in the world, that cannot digeſt the knowen truth, but continually addict themſelues to nouelties: for proofe of this,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>T. C.</item>
                        <item>I. P.</item>
                        <item>I. D.</item>
                        <item>I. P.</item>
                        <item>T. C.</item>
                        <item>G. W.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </note> no ſinging in the Church is lawfull: afterward the ſinging of the Pſalmes was lawfull. The Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaieth a fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſelected are and may bee vſed: The Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaieth <hi>Penrie,</hi> concerne not vs, therefore not to be vſed in diuine ſeruice. Allegations of fathers and councels are impious, aſſertions of fathers and decrees of councels ſaieth one that ſhal be nameleſſe, may be vſed. Sermons preached with premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, derogate, from the maieſty of God, <hi>dabitur vobis in illa ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra:</hi> Sermons preached without premeditation, they are but far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels of verball diuinity. Innouations in doctrine, in religion, are dangerous, <hi>Endoxius,</hi> and <hi>Acacius</hi> peruerted the greeke Church, and as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> in his 9. booke of his eccleſiaſtical hiſtorie c. 46. <hi>Men</hi> ſaieth he, <hi>were ſo raſh, that they did contemne the cuſtome of the Church, &amp; nouas leges ſibi pro ſe quiſque conderet,</hi> euery man had a religion peculiar vnto himſelfe: and is not this verified among vs at this day? and what is the reaſon thereof? men are caried awaie with a ſhew of doctrine, ſo head-ſtrong, that they will not ſtande to the iudgement of the Church: corruption in maners, in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are very rife, all haue erred, and the trueth is reuealed but
<pb facs="tcp:25165:7"/> vnto a fewe, and that is vnto them. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> would haue all things done <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in decent and good order, and according to ordinance: but our conformers are ſo repugnant vnto that, as the Poet ſpeaketh, <hi>qui rectum nil eſſe putat, quod non facit ipſe decorum:</hi> that they labour to controule the cuſtome of the Church, &amp; to call in queſtion controuerſies already decided, and to auoide an inconuenience,<note place="margin">Epiphan. in Anchorato.</note> they doe as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſpeaketh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, flying away from the ſmoke, they fall into the fire. Falſe Prophets there are among the people, ſo likewiſe there ſhall be falſe teachers among you. The Church of Chriſt hath not bene free from this malady. <hi>Maſter, didſt thou not ſow good corne in thy fielde: from whence came theſe tares?</hi> The Church is ſaied to be <hi>Columba vnica;</hi> his onely Doue: <hi>via directa,</hi> a direct way. The Church is ſaied to be <hi>vnica, quia in vnitate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit,</hi> becauſe ſhe conſiſteth in vnity: <hi>ſancta,</hi> holy; becauſe ſhee is ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt, and becauſe ſhee is the piller &amp; the foundation of trueth: and ſaied to be <hi>corpus Chriſti,</hi> he himſelfe the head. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Timot.</hi> 3. ſhee is ſaied to bee <hi>vniuerſalis,</hi> becauſe ſhee is not onely reſident in one place, but is extended to the confines of the whole earth. The ſame affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Iſidorus</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de officijs eccleſiaſticis cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Aluarus, Pelagius, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de planctu eccleſiae art:</hi> 65. <hi>Torquemada lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de eccleſia c.</hi> 13. The church was inſtituted in paradiſe, &amp; after the fal of our firſt parents being barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe became fertle, watered with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloode of Ieſus Chriſt: the benefit whereof, we all haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and ſhal continue to the ende of the world, and the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt her. Are wee all agreed of a Church? and of the vnity thereof? from whence ariſe theſe diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? the <hi>Seruetian,</hi> he hath a Church by himſelfe, and is his the true Church? the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> he is a member of the true Church, therefore he cannot miſcary? The <hi>Familie of loue,</hi> he is of the true Church: <hi>Frauncis Ket</hi> oppoſeth himſelfe againſt them all, for his reaſons and allegations are of themſelues ſo euident, that they cannot be anſwered. Our <hi>Puritanes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> are now a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Church in taking away humane traditions, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary ceremonies, and will offer vp a Church pure, vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, without ſpot. If ancient <hi>Hilarie</hi> were aliue at this day,<note place="margin">Hilar. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantium Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtum.</note> and ſhould ſee vs contend at noone day, in the heate of ſommer <hi>de Aſini vmbra:</hi> I am very well aſſured he would vſe the ſame words
<pb facs="tcp:25165:8"/> that he did long ago whenas the like occaſion was offered in his time: <hi>periculoſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſerabile eſt, tot nunc fides exiſtere, quot voluntates:</hi> It is lamentable that there ſhould be as many ſeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral faithes, as there are diuerſities in wils. <hi>Et tot nobis doctrinas eſſe, quot mores.</hi> And as many cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of maners, ſo many diuerſities in doctrin; <hi>Et tot cauſas blasphemtaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pullulare quot vitia ſunt,</hi> &amp; as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vices, ſo many cauſes of blaſphemy, ſith that we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to this point, that we wil haue one faith write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to our will, or els the expoſition thereof ſhall bee according to our direction. Thus ſpake this Ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t father of his time, I appeale to you whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe wordes of his are not veried among vs in theſe daies? But is the Church of England throughly purged? What obſtacles haue you remoued? Aſſuredly the Reuenues Eccleſiaſticall, Biſhoprickes and Deaneries, Cathedrall Churches, haue beene obſtacles vnto them, for had they beene able to remoue theſe they had brought in <hi>Idaeam Platonicam</hi> the like vnto this at anie time ſhould neuer haue bene knowen. But God hath taken the raigne into his own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; hath put a ſnaffle into their mouthes, and hath aſſwaged the corages of them, that to run forward they cannot, and the vigilant eie of our ſoueraigne hath cauſed them like Seriphian frogges to liue in ſilence, and whereas heretofore the hole Realme hath ſwarmed with there bookes the date of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is now expired, &amp; God graunt them grace that in time they may ſee there owne infirmities, and al occaſions of diſſention taken a way, we may liue togither in Chriſtian vnity, that in this world we we may ſo glorifie God, that into the world to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e we al likewiſe may be glorified of him. It were not altogither repugnant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this matter, if a queſtion were demaunded wherefore God permitteth his Church to be perſecuted by falſe Apoſtles, falſe teachers. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t qui in vobis ſunt manifeſti fiant,</hi> to this end, that their good and beſt men among you may be made manifeſt. A grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter puniſhment cannot be laied vpon vs then this, when as God as <hi>Aug.</hi> ſpeaketh in his 19 ſermon <hi>de verbis Apoſtoli</hi> permitteth vs to be ſeduced by them, they which make a glorious ſhew of piety &amp; religion: &amp; in the end they bring both ſoule &amp; body to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arrius deluded Irene the Empres with hipocriſie, Menno the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſt corrupted multitudes with the ſame, <hi>Caſtellio</hi> infected with phariſaical leuen was the ouerthrow of himſelfe &amp; his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, and as <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerueth: writing to <hi>Lucilius,</hi> there is no he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſie,
<pb facs="tcp:25165:8"/> be it neuer ſo peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but carieth a reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. The D. ſpake in paradiſe, but how, in the forme of a ſerpent. There is no place be it neuer ſo wel fenced &amp; garded, but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil wil intrude himſelfe, &amp; he that ſpake to <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in paradiſe, in the likenes of a ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to the which of <hi>Endor</hi> &amp; to <hi>Saule</hi> in the likenes of <hi>Samuel</hi> to the Iews in the likenes of <hi>Moſes</hi> to benefit himſelfe wil eaſily be perſwaded to deceiue us to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſforme himſelfe into the likenes of an angel of light.<note place="margin">Georgius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drenus lib. <hi>2.</hi> Annal. ad Jſaſi. com.</note> Therfore it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to look into our own eſtate, not to addict our ſelues to diuerſities of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; to be caried away with any blaſt, reſident in no one place like wandering ſtarres and like <hi>Euripus</hi> beeing alwaies in motion like the raging waues of the ſea, we caſt forth our owne ſhame. I ſay that, ſaith the Apoſtle that each of you ſaith, I hold with <hi>Paul</hi> I am with <hi>Cephas,</hi> I am with <hi>Apollo,</hi> and what are all theſe but the miniſters of Chriſt. And in theſe daies the laity of <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> is ſo preiudiciall, that if they once haue conceiued an opinion of one preacher, preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly they magnifie thar one aboue the clouds, &amp; labour to bring the other in conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt: this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a good liuer, a right <hi>Cephas,</hi> he canot abide circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion, no ceremonies, &amp; <hi>Apollos</hi> a mighty man in the ſcripture, able to put al my Lord B. in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> to ſilence, what learning there is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cealed in any of theſe I know not, I come not hitherto diſgrace any: but wel I am aſſured, that this popular applauſe of our laity, hath cauſed ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry meane ſchol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers to ſtep vp into the pulpit, the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whereof the right reuerend fathers the Biſhops of this land, haue to their no ſmall griefe already found. And this malady <hi>S. Aug.</hi> found in his time as hee confeſſeth in his booke <hi>de anima ad Renatum, illud eſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtum &amp; periculoſum vel pernicioſum, ſi cum laudatur eloquenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a perſuadetur inſipientia vt in praetioſo poculo bibatur peſtifera po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io.</hi> This is a da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous matter ſaith he, that one ſhal preſume of himſelfe ſo far aboue his reach in that he is not able to performe halfe that is expected at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, in the mean ſeaſon his ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is detected &amp; his doctrine ſcorned, from hence ſpringeth diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalus to the church of God: the waring of a dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the church as a Cap or a Sirples is ſuperſtitious: vnlearned men haue we ſpred this in corners &amp; vnlearned men maintaine it publikely that as <hi>Hierom</hi> writeth <hi>ad Demetriadem virgine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feruentiſſimi in terrenis fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidiſſimi in caeleſtibus ſumus &amp; ſumma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in rebus paruis exhibentes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem ad maiora torpeſcimus:</hi> In things that doe not concerne vs
<pb facs="tcp:25165:9"/> we are very carefull but in matters that doe concerne vs, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we take no care at all. <hi>Luther</hi> in his time found no inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenicence in them, in ſo much that he vſed them. <hi>Eraſmus ad fratres inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Germaniae</hi> was ſo farre from condemning them, that he defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, if <hi>Caluin</hi> or <hi>Beza</hi> haue exclamed againſt them as abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſcandalous.<note place="margin">Caluinus ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorem Helueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Beza ad Edm: Grindallum Epiſcop: Londi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſem Epi. <hi>38,</hi>
               </note> Yet <hi>Caluine</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> founde at the laſt that they might be vſed, and no offence at all in the vſing. Wherefore ſhould we contend beloued ſo ſeriouſly for nothing, &amp; make our ſelues ridiculous to the ſight of the world, and to leaue that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that was bequeathed vnto vs, and now to begin to frame a new doctrine, the which as <hi>Hilarie</hi> writeth <hi>ad Conſtantium Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtum: ſcribendae &amp; innouandae fidei vſus inoleuit,</hi> it is a common cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to euery one to haue a new faieth, a new religion: <hi>qui poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam noua potius caepit condere quam accepta retinere, nec veterata de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit, nec innouata firmauit,</hi> &amp; hauing one according to our humor, we neither regarde the olde faieth, neither doe we labour to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the new religion, <hi>&amp; facta eſt fides temporum potius quam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and our faith doth more fit the preſent time, then the courſe of Scripture. Men and brethren, I haue beene ſomewhat long in theſe points, I will leaue them to your good conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: in the meane time, let vs be aſſured of this, that God permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this cockle and darnell to grow among vs, vntill in due time he flingeth them into the fire. And if wee perſiſt in theſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, God he will ſeperate himſelfe from vs, and leaue vs to our owne direction, and then we ſhall very well perceaue, that it is a fearefull thing to fall into the handes of the liuing God, And happie and bleſſed is he, that hath eſcaped the heat of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, for our God is a conſuming fire.</p>
            <p>The cauſes that moued our profeſſed enemies to ſende forth theſe teachers are diuerſe: among the which I wil at this time ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue one, and that is, the ſhort continuance that he hath in this world, the reaſon is in that he furmiſed, that this worlde is langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and lieth at the laſt gaſpe, and by reaſon the time is ſhort, he doeth not omit any oportunity, diuerſe are allured with an externall ſhew of piety, others are caried away with a perſuaſiue hope of permanent felicity, ſome are drowned in deſpaire: in fine, there is but one way to heauen and the by-waies and croſſe paths that leade to hell, are Innumerable. <hi>Bernard</hi> lamenting the diſordered liues of the Cleargy in his time, compared them
<pb facs="tcp:25165:9"/> to conduit pipes the which yeeld water vnto vs plentifuully, but in fine reſerue none themſelues, ſo theſe that ſpeake wel, and doe ill, in ſending forth a ſhrill ſound vnto others, benefit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues nothing at all. <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> writing vpon the 9, of <hi>Geneſis</hi> affirmeth that the prieſtes in his time were diſordered, in that they reſerued the Reuenues of the Church to their owne pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culiar vſe and in the end he concludeth, <hi>exorti ſunt in eccleſia gigan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes qui potius videntur reges quam epiſcopt.</hi> The prieſts ſaith he are ſo ſumptuous in their diet, and ſo prodigal in ſuperfluous expences that they liue more like princes, then prieſts. <hi>Bernard</hi> that liued 5. hundred yeares agoe lamenting the irregular behauiour of his time, <hi>noſtri praelati facti ſunt pilati, noſtri paſtores facti ſunt tonſores,</hi> and in another place <hi>plus calcaria quam altaria fulgent.</hi> Is the cleargy of <hi>England</hi> in this point ſo reformed as at their hands is required? I will not defend any where he is faulty, we are full gorged, we haue aboundance, plenty is harbored among vs and there is no complaining in our ſtreetes. Our children they are brought vp i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely, I will not ſay lewdly, fewe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will follow there fathers in this ſpirituall function, &amp; what is the reaſon thereof. Aſſure your ſelues beloued our ſpirituall landes are turned into temporalles, hundreds by the yeare, are not ſufficient to maitaine them, this is ſcandalous to the eie of the multitude, and their diſordered liues are laied as heauy burdens vpon the backes of their aged pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rents. <hi>Bona eccleſiae, bona pauperum.</hi> But it is nowe inuerted. God hee prouided for there parentes aboue their expectation, &amp; is not God able to prouide aſwell for them, in the meane ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manie an hungry belly is not filled, manie naked are not clothed the halt, the diſeaſed, the blinde lie in the ſtreetes, and are not called to bee refreſhed, and the reaſon is, in that our ſonnes and daughters muſt bee made ſpectacles for euery one to gaſe vpon: and adorned like Lords, and ladies, they forget their owne ſtate, and the honorable calling of their parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Roterodame</hi> writing to a frend of his in <hi>Germanie</hi> certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth him of the death of two famous and learned men in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the greateſt patrons that he had the one,<note place="margin">Farrag. Epiſt. lib. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> was <hi>William War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Lord Chancelor of England and Archbiſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the latter end of the raigne of Henry the 7. and the greateſt part of the raigne of Henry the 8. he liued <hi>vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad decrepita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> etatem</hi> This man had many children the which he kept for charity ſome
<pb facs="tcp:25165:10"/> at the Vniuerſities, others that were not ingenious he diſburſed a ſum of money, and placed them in an occupation, for his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that were fatherles and motherles, fearing leaſt they ſhould encline to leudnes, he gaue not many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreds as we doe in theſe daies, but a competent dowry of twenty nobles, and beſtowed them to their great likings. This man was ſummoned by ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to depart out of this world, three houres before his departure he called his treaſorer vnto him, charging him to bring vnto him his accompts, that hee might make euen with the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he departed, the which when he had done, it was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the olde Biſhop was not in debt: and that he had in redy money a great maſſe of currant coyne 10. pounds: 10. pounds, O ſaith he <hi>ſatis viatici,</hi> there is enough for me to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the way, I haue but a ſhort iourney to take, &amp; forthwith departed. The other was <hi>Iohn Colet</hi> a cuntry ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mine born in <hi>London,</hi> vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al his fathers lands, &amp; ſubſtance came, by reaſon of the death of all his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, 22.<note place="margin">Eraſ. ad Jodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Jonam.</note> he had, &amp; it pleaſed god to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al away this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excepted. I neede not to tel you what he did his ſchoole at my back can tel you, he hath ſent forth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce heretofore many a famous ſchol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, that haue proued neceſſary &amp; profitable me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the church of god. This learned father hath left yet ſomwhat to be finiſhed by ſome of you, whom it hath pleaſed God, not to bleſſe with chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the which hauing borne all offices belonging to this Citty, and liuing in great wealth and abundance, craueth of you, that you would ioyne with him, in begetting children, ſpirituall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Chriſt, that where ſome of you haue not a child, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers likewiſe but one, that you would follow the example of that famous and honourable gentleman Sir <hi>Thomas Wight,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome part of your liuings, vpon ſome one poore Colledge or other in <hi>Oxforde</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> that once a yeare there might be a free election, that thoſe children whoſe parents are poore, might according to their deſert be preferred in the Colledge to a ſcholler-ſhip or fellow-ſhip, I doubt not, but the ſmoke of this incenſe would aſcend like a ſweete perfume in the noſtrels of or God.</p>
            <p>As there were falſe Prophets among the people, ſo likewiſe there ſhall bee falſe teachers among you. Among manye plagues vvherewith God did afflict and puniſh his people, this was the greateſt, that for their contempt and diſobedience of
<pb facs="tcp:25165:10"/> his people, he would giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their hearts deſire, he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to be ſeduced by euery ſpirit. Doth God afflict his people by famine, vpon their repentaunce hee ſendeth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: doth hee afflict them vvith peſtilence vpon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, the plague ceaſeth. Doeth hee afflict them with war God at their amendment, hee breaketh the bowe and ſpeare inſunder, and ouerthroweth all the chariots and horſemen of the AEgyptians, and cauſeth the violent vvaues of <hi>Iordan</hi> to returne backewarde, and deliuereth his people in great ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from imminent dangers by the handes of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</hi> But are his people light headed? Will they haue Gods to goe before them as the heathen haue, this light meate in the wilderneſſe cloyeth vs, it is not comparable in any degree, to the fleſh pots of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> the tabernacle of <hi>Moloch,</hi> and the ſtarre of <hi>Rempham,</hi> their Altars vvhereon they vſed to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the body of their Sonnes and Daughters to deuils: all theſe aſcended vp into the preſence of God, and then they neglected the due ſeruice of God, and laied open their eares to the inchantments of falſe Prophets, and brought a ſpeedy deſtruction vpon them, <hi>haec loquutus eſt Dominus,</hi> thus ſaieth the Lord vvhen I haue not ſaied it. Among many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences that the Church ſuſteyneth, this is the greateſt, that the ſimpleſt and the vnlearnedſt among vs, are eaſily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to take vpon them the expoſition of Gods booke, and a phantaſie beeing once conceiued can hardly bee remooued. This cauſed <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> in an Epiſtle that he writeth to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noratus,</hi> to lament the folly of certaine in his age: <hi>Nulla imbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poetica diſciplina, Terentium ſine magiſtro attingere non auderet,</hi> he that is ignorant in poetry, hee will not preſume to take <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> in his hande and expounde him, <hi>Asper, Cornutus, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> his interpreters are had in great reuerence and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>vt quilibet poeta poſſit intelligi,</hi> for this cauſe that euery Poet bee hee neuer ſo harde and obſcure, may the eaſier bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode, <hi>Tu in ſanctos libros ſine duce irruis, &amp; de his ſine preceptore audes ferre ſententiam?</hi> Wilt thou then ſaieth <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> beeing vnlearned, vvithout a guide take vpon thee to expounde Scripture? The like hath <hi>Saint Ambroſe</hi> in his thirde booke <hi>de fide ad Gratianum,</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> vvriting to <hi>Paulinus,</hi> is copious in this argument and <hi>Leo</hi> his Epiſt. 33. <hi>ad
<pb facs="tcp:25165:11"/> Theodoſium.</hi> I ſpeak this the more confidently in that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are thought to be ſo eaſie, that the ſimpleſt may read and vnderſtand them, and what hath followed, diuerſe haue prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their owne fantaſie before the right and perfect expoſition. Laymen haue in their nocturnall conuenticles preſumed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete the ſame, and the weaker ſort likewiſe, whom <hi>Saint Paul</hi> in any wiſe would not permit to teach, haue peruerted the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie meanes of ſaluation to their owne deſtruction. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> a ſeruant and Cooke to <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour, intruding himſelfe into that ſecret conference that the Emperour had with <hi>Baſil,</hi> as you may reade in the tripartite hiſtory, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 36. had texts of Scripture ſo rife and copious in his mouth, that the old father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to muſe, vnto what ende all his textuall cotations tended. Sir Cooke ſaieth he, <hi>tuum eſt de pulmentarijs cogitare, non dogmata diuina decoquere:</hi> Maſter Cooke ſaith he, if I be not deceiued, your office belongeth to the ſeaſoning of the pot, and in matters ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to Gods Church you haue no intereſt. Reade belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Scriptures with feare and reuerence, preferre not a priuate interpretation before that which hath beene receaued, and is approued a truth. If any be ignorant, let him repaire to the learned, that all ſects &amp; ſchiſmes and falſe teachers detected, we may ſo heare, reade and beleeue the Scriptures, that they may be vnto vs a ſauor of life vnto life, that the courſe of our life ended, each of vs may receaue a full reward in the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the which God for his mercy make vs all partakers. And thus much, by your fauourable patience ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of this firſt part.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part conteineth a deſcription of them: they ſhall bring in damnable hereſies tending to the deſtruction of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer and the inſtructed, they ſhall impugne the deity and the humanity of Chriſt: the people that are credulous ſhal follow them, the trueth ſhal be blaſphemed and corrupted by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; of a greedy appetite, to enrich themſelues, with pleaſing and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſiue words, they ſhall buy &amp; ſel you according to their owne diſpoſition. The Apoſtle writing to the Hebrewes, exhorteth them not to be caried away with ſtrange doctrine, from heauen, to earth, from Angels, to damned ſpirits, from faith, to infidelity, from felicity, to miſery, and in fine, to euery miſchiefe: for they that leaue faith, hope, and charity, and with the contrary vnto
<pb facs="tcp:25165:11"/> theſe doe conuerſe, are forthwith caried into eternall damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being of the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they degenerate and are of the ſeede of <hi>Cain:</hi> deſcending lineally of Chriſt, they approue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of the ſeede of Antichriſt, <hi>Iude</hi> exhorteth all Chriſtians to remember the words of the Apoſtles of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which tolde you, that in the later daies there ſhould come moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, which ſhould walk according to their carnall deſires: world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded men hauing not the ſpirit. Our ſauiour in the 18. of <hi>Luke,</hi> the ſon of man whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, doe you think that he ſhal find faith vpon the earth? And againe, take heede of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that come vnto you in ſheeps cloathing, yet inwardly they are rauening wolues, whereunto the Apoſtle addeth this, that they ſhall make merchandize of godlineſſe, and as our Sauiour ſpeaketh vnder a pretence of piety, they ſhall deuoure widowes houſes. Whoſoeuer, ſaieth Chriſt is not with me, is againſt me, &amp; he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth abroade: profeſſour of Chriſt and profeſſed enemies to Chriſt, gathering multitudes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether and diſperſers of them, whoſe ende ſhall be according to their workes.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is preached to many: beleeued of a fewe: ſome require diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in the Church of Chriſt, the whip of Chriſt is not exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the ſtreight way is laied open for euery paſſenger and liberty ſtandeth at the gate and offereth free acceſſe to euery one, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are incredulous, Maſter we would ſee a ſigne from thee: an extraordinary ſigne would ſufficiently approue thy doctrine. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> flew vp into the aire as he corrupted men on earth,<note place="margin">Arnobius lib. <hi>2,</hi> cont. gentes.</note> he would if it might be, peruert Angels in heauen: but his ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the princes of the aire, forſooke him, and let go their holde, and as ſinne of it ſelfe is heauy, ſo likewiſe at the voice of <hi>Peter,</hi> downe fel <hi>Simon</hi> the man of ſinne, and the fal of him is a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable preſident for curioſity: hereupon <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> in his 22. booke <hi>de ciuitate Dei. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>quiſquis adhuc prodigia vt credat inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium qua mundo credente non credit:</hi> he that to ratifie his faith, requireth a wonder, that man ſaieth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is a wonder, that ſtandeth in doubt of his faith, when all the world receaueth the ſame. Chriſt and Chriſtianity cannot be ſeperated: Luciferians, Vigilantians, Donatiſts, Anababtiſts, and as many as glory in the bare title of any man: theſe haue ſeparated themſelues from Chriſt, and are none of his folde.
<pb facs="tcp:25165:12"/> 
               <hi>Ignoro Miletium, Paulinum respuo, &amp; qui Chriſtiani non eſt,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſaieth <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> I neither care for the one or the other, I am aſſured of one thing ſaieth <hi>Hierom,</hi> that hee that is not vvith Chriſt, is againſt Chriſt. Sathan hath ſent forth his meſſengers, I came ſaieth Chriſt in the name of my father, and you receaued me not. Another hath come in his his owne name, and him you haue receaued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> in the Reuelation are abroade, and their armies are as the ſandes of the ſea. The <hi>gnoſtique heretique</hi> that ſprang from the rotten roote of <hi>Carpocrates,</hi> they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded piety and integritie of life, and practiſed ſecretly by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gique: <hi>Arrius</hi> he perceiued that the deity of Chriſt was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally receaued, in that hee was tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee likewiſe peruerted multitudes in adding a letter, and drowned the ſame in the ſounde, affirming, that Chriſt was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not of the ſame ſubſtance vvith God his father, but of the like, and brought vpon his owne heade ſuddaine deſtruction: Chriſt is very God and very man, God of his father before the world, and man of his Mother borne in the world, perfect God and perfect man, his humane fleſh ſubſiſting. Yet <hi>Ioannes Langius</hi> affirmed, that Chriſt was not man, whoſe damnable hereſie vvas long ago condemned in <hi>Eutiches,</hi> in the 3. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> Councels, and the 2. councels helde at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Chriſt became ſinne, that is, hee offered himſelfe to God the father a ſacrifice for ſinne, hee died for the ſinnes of the worlde: if any preſumptuous and blaſphemous mouth will ſaye, that there vvas ſinne in Chriſt. <hi>Anathema ſit,</hi> let him bee accurſed, I hope there is no preacher in <hi>Englande</hi> will ſay ſo, if any haue affirmed it, that man is in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of hereſie and blaſphemy, and if he perſiſt in the ſame, I aſſure him, little comfort ſhall hee reape by the paſſion of Chriſt: for the benefit of his paſsion is extended <hi>in omnes pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores,</hi> but as <hi>Durand</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>respicientes,</hi> but vnto them that haue conceiued within themſelues a godly ſorrow for ſinne the grace of God aſsiſting. If then this doctrine be true, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controuerſie it is moſt true, where are they which vvere tearmed patropaſsiani and the like, from vvhence <hi>Michaell Seruetus</hi> deriued his execrable and damnable aſſertions op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite and repugnant to the analogy and proportion of
<pb facs="tcp:25165:12"/> our faith.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſuffered in his humanity, the deity impaſsible,<note place="margin">Lutherus in <hi>2.</hi> ca. ep. <hi>1.</hi> Petri.</note> 
               <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> defended the contrary and vvas ouer-reached, Chriſt deſcended into hell, and preached vnto the ſpirits that vvere in priſon: here <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Rhetrodame</hi> decyphered his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball diuinity, and his Atheiſme, in affirming, that the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt extended it ſelfe ſo farre, that it releaſed the ſoules of <hi>Cicero, Homer, Plato, Socrates.</hi> If any learned man doubt of this his aſſertion: I refer him to his epiſtle vvriten <hi>Iacobo Tutori.</hi> Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe daies are curious: <hi>Eraſmus</hi> he miſliked the old interpreter: <hi>Beza</hi> miſliked him, <hi>Caſtellio</hi> condemned him, <hi>Tremelius</hi> magnified of a number: <hi>Vatablus</hi> little regarded our ordinary tranſlation of the Bible in Engliſh, in pulpits not long ſince reprehended. What haue theſe procured but a defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from Chriſt and Chriſtianity: <hi>Laurentius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alla</hi> in his ſixt booke of Elegances cap. 34 by nomeanes could be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to allowe of the woorde <hi>perſona</hi> in the Trinity:<note place="margin">Jouius in vitis virorum illuſtrium.</note> 
               <hi>Pomponius Laetus</hi> had conceiued ſo pleaſing an opinion of himſelfe, that hee vtterly deteſted the Greeke tongue, in that hee feared it would corrupt his fluent and copious ſtile in Latine. And oftentimes it falleth out, that men ſtanding too much in their owne light forgette themſelues, and are perſwaded of a verity, the vvhich of them is not conceiued: ſectes are rife among vs, the trueth is blaſphemed, and diuerſe in theſe daies for lucre ſake to obtayne a poore benefice can preach according to the direction of the patrons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> beeing once corrupted by money by <hi>Legates,</hi> proteſted that he had little to ſay in the behalfe of his King and Countrey, for his tongue was not his ovvne, in that hee had ſolde it: ſo theſe <hi>Clurina peccora,</hi> that vvith money cary deaneries and preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries vpon their backes, they haue but litle to ſay in the church of God, for they paide extremely for it, &amp; if they may ſaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he careth not.</p>
            <p>It vvas an oulde verſe <hi>Curia Romana non captat ouem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lana,</hi> ſo they maye reape the benefite, lette them that liſt take the laboure. And that vvhich is a ſoule incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience, vvhen menne that haue ſpente all their dayes in phiſicke, or in the ſtudies of the Ciuill Lawe, if hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:25165:13"/> by that aſpire to promotion preſently he intrudeth himſelfe into the miniſtry, and with their fleſh hookes like <hi>Elies</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſnatch the fleſh out of the pot which in equity belonged to the prieſt, and not vnto them. In the meane ſeaſon, many a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſcholler in the vniuerſity, whoſe frends are poore, lingereth away his daies and is not regarded. Our patrones ſhould be vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in this point: but euery man prouideth for his owne, one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſupporteth 4 ſteeples on his ſhoulders, like <hi>Atlas</hi> that ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth heauen, that by reaſon of his burden he cannot ſpeake. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed their patrimonies in chambering &amp; wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe and exceſſiue Rioting they forthwith take ſanctuary in ſome one Cathedrall Church or other, and are prebendes in the ſame. The Church of God feeleth the inconuenience of it. And as yet, it is not redreſſed. Hereſies creepe into the Church of God ſects and diuiſions abound, the way of trueth is blaſphemed and diuers are caried away with faire and pleaſant ſpeeches. <hi>Lucian</hi> in a treatiſe that he writeth <hi>de non credendo calumniae.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a ſeducer crept in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong you well furniſhed with learning this man ſaieth he would with great diligence bee regarded: leſt in the end hee ſeduce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Are theſe teachers in outward ſhew religious? auoid them, for as Leo ſpeaketh in his 9. Sermon <hi>ac qudrageſima, plus plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li eſt in inſidiatore occulto quam in hoſte manifeſto:</hi> there is more daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſaieth he in him that is not detected, then in a profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Matters that nothing at all concerne vs haue bene ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to the Church of God. Auguſtine and <hi>Hierom</hi> contended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the gourd of <hi>Ionas. Hierom</hi> and <hi>Ruffinus</hi> whither <hi>Origen</hi> were ſaued: <hi>Aug.</hi> in his 17. booke <hi>de ciuitate Dei</hi> cap. 20 doubteth wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Solomon</hi> were ſaued ſo doeth <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in the 68. <hi>homily</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Alphonſus Abulenſis</hi> writing vpon the 2 of <hi>Reg.</hi> cap. 7. <hi>quaeſtione vltima.</hi> Thoſe thinges that doe not concerne vs, let vs not contend about them, wee haue no ſuch cuſtome, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of God. Let vs not ſearch into the miſteries of God, for what man is he that is able to comprehend them?</p>
            <p>Pride is properly incident vnto theſe teachers, and as <hi>Aug.</hi> ſpeaketh it is <hi>mater omnium haereticorum.</hi> The wiſdome of man it is fooliſhnes with God, of our ſelues wee are not able to thinke a good thought, much leſſe to perfourme any thing that is good.
<pb facs="tcp:25165:13"/> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> compareth the night oule to theſe kinde of men,<note place="margin">Ambr. in Hexa.</note> 
               <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal iſt ud haereticorum figura eſt qui tenebras amplectuntur diaboli luce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaluatoris horreſcunt:</hi> this creature ſaieth hee, is a right and perfect figure of heretiques, which delight in palpable darckeneſſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the deuill, and cannot abide the light of Chriſt, <hi>&amp; gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus diſputationum oculis cernunt vana non respiciunt ſempiterna,</hi> and with their great eies of contention they looke after vanity, and regard not thoſe things that concerne eternity <hi>acuti ad ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa,</hi> quickſighthd to ſpy ſuperſtition, <hi>hebetes ad diuina,</hi> ſlowe and very dull in Chriſtian Religion, <hi>qui dum ſe putant ſub limibus euolare ſermonibus</hi> by which perſwade themſelues to flee into heauen with great words, <hi>tanquam noctuae veri luminis splendore turbantur:</hi> like vnto night oules are throwen downe at the bright<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of the true light.</p>
            <p>A man infected with ſome one dangerous malady is auoided: for as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaketh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an infection is alwaies in <hi>motu,</hi> forthwith it will diſperſe herſelfe. But the infection of the ſoule, which is hereſie as <hi>Bernarde</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>ſerpit vt cancer,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we think it is going away from vs, it commeth vpon vs that is not regarded. The body being ſicke, we forthwith haue recourſe to ſundry expert phyſicians, and be the diſeaſe neuer ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, one or other is perſwaded that he can cure the ſame. But the ſoule of man lying in a conſumption, that the very eſſence of Religion, faith in Chriſt is almoſt brought to nothing, few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort vnto him, that with clay and ſpittle can open our eies: whoſe hem of his grame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can immediatly ſtay the iſſue of bloud, who in ſaying: <hi>puella tibi dico ſurge,</hi> damſell I ſay to thee ariſe, who can raiſe the dead to life, who waketh <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of his ſounde ſleepe, <hi>Lazare veni foras, Lazarus</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e forth? This phyſician is not ſought nor regarded, but it is with vs, as with deſperate patients, when the phyſician perceiueth that there is no way but death, leaueth the patient to his owne appetite, ſo <hi>ducimus in laetis dies noſtros, &amp; in puncto ad inferos, deſcendimus</hi> we keepe holy day al the yeare long, and in the twinckling of any eye, we are turned into the pit. We are al perſwaded of a trueth, yet we are not reſolued of the trueth, much like to the goaſt that in his trau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce paſquill diſcerned houering in the ſphear of the Moone with a weighty ſtone at his heeles, that gladly would aſcend higher, yet the loue that he bare to the world did keep him downe, this was <hi>Eraſmus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25165:14"/> of <hi>Roterodame</hi> that knew the trueth, and yet for feare of looſing his dignities, in the world durſt not profeſſe the ſame. He that de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nieth me before man, I will likewiſe deny him before my father in heauen: he that confeſſeth me before man, I likewiſe will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him before my father in heauen. That man that wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the cogniſance of a noble man, and vnder him is protected from diuerſe that lie in waite to ſlay him, and receauing ſundrie benefits of him, doeth in eury place reuile and ſlaunder him, he is vnworthy of his benefites already receaued: ſo wee that beare the cogniſance of Chriſt, &amp; vnder him are protected from three capitall enemies, the world, the fleſh, and the diuel, that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lye in waite to kill both ſoule and body, doe keepe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of his profeſſed enemies, and aſſociate our ſelues with pride, luxurie and prodigality, and with them little eſteeme of him and his Croſſe: we approue our ſelues vnprofitable ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and greater iniurie then theſe vnto him, cannot be offered. If we profeſſe Chriſt in outward ſhewe, for feare of the Rigour of ſome penall ſtatute, and in our harts doe not beleeue in him, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ours ſerueth not. So the diuels likewiſe know him and acknowledge him, yet they beleeue not in him. In the meane ſeaſon we are ſecure, euery one doubteth not his owne eſtate, <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedra Moſis,</hi> the chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and we haue <hi>Abraham</hi> to our father, but theſe auaile not: diuiſion is crept in among vs: a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome deuided in it ſelfe cannot ſtand, <hi>concordia res paruae creſcunt diſcordia mazimae dilabuntur. Antioch</hi> a famous Citty, as you may read in the 11. of the <hi>Acts.</hi> in that the faithful beleeuing were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, a Citty greatly honored for Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: in ſo much, it was had in ſo great honour and reputation that the patriarch had vnder him: 14 metropolitanes, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olaterane</hi> in his 11. book reporteth, there were an hundred and fifty Biſhops. The Cittie double walled, for it had foure hundred and threefcore ſtrong towers, and three hundred threeſcore beautifull Churches, but what of theſe, they were at diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſome followed the doctrin of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> others relied wholly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Macarius,</hi> denying the ſonne of God that redeemed them. Inſomuch that God being offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Coſroe</hi> king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> inuaded the Citty, ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth it, put the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to fire &amp; ſword, &amp; this eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had ſchiſm &amp; diuiſion. To let paſſe <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered by the <hi>Turke,</hi> to omit the Empire of <hi>Trapez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> vanquiſhed by him, in that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb facs="tcp:25165:14"/> diſſeuered themſelues in matters of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that the Greeke Church diſſented from the latin: the Emperor of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> came with the Patriarch to a councel holden at <hi>Florence</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; there confirmed the vnity of both Churches, what follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed? <hi>Marcus</hi> B. of <hi>Epheſus</hi> kindled ſedition, peruerted the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in 14. years after, made great variance among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: inſomuch, that the <hi>Turke</hi> came ſuddainly vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered the Empire, and put them al to the ſword: the Emperour in fleeing away was ſlaine, his head caried vpon a pole in deriſion, his wife &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters reſerued to ſatisfie their carnall appetite. This is the ende of ſects and ſchiſme. In the time, of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 9. Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Platina in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Joh. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> when as barbariſme had ouer run all <hi>Italy,</hi> inſomuch, that we read nothing worthy memory to haue beene done in that age, that is reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to poſterity: there was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a monſter, in proportion like vnto a man, his head excepted, and that was like vnto a dog, the which reſembled the eſtate and condition of that time, for ſo long as in hand and foote we cary the ſhape of a man, if wee haue not that reaſon and diſcretion that is giuen vnto vs by God, but according to our appetite, follw that which is not expedient for vs, we approue our ſelues in the end more like beaſts then men, the queſtion at this day betwixt vs &amp; the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we fel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or they from vs. There is ſay they, no change, no innouatious in our doctrin, that which was deliuered vnto vs, we haue receaued, &amp; that which we receaued, haue we preached &amp; beleeued. Is this true; all of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agree in it: what is the reaſon that in their Maſſe of late years, there haue bene ſuch ſundry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouations &amp; alterations. <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. defended in his time, that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Maſſe which was <hi>ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſum Sarum:</hi> ſo did <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> the 7. yet <hi>Paulus</hi> the 4. he began to vary a little from it. Afterwarde came <hi>Pius</hi> the 5. and he <hi>ſub anathemate ſanxit,</hi> none to be authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall but that which hee allowed: <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. he liked not of his, &amp; he ſet out one according as he thought expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: afterward <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. he cauſed a new one to printed at <hi>Rome</hi> with his additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which in the year 1588. was printed by <hi>Plantine</hi> at <hi>Andwerp. Tho: Stapleton,</hi> he exclameth againſt vs for our ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. In that <hi>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the 8. leſt his 6. articles in force: <hi>Edw.</hi> the 6. he put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not in ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; her M. hath varied fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both. Beloued I knowe no cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge or alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our doctrine, the book of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praier is the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e now, that it was at the firſt, hir M. hath defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>narchs of <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; in great lenity ſhe hath gouerned vs &amp; peace
<pb facs="tcp:25165:15"/> hath lodged within the wals of our Citties: I pray God long to continue the ſame euen to the laſt generation. <hi>Gregory Martin</hi> in his diſcouery of corruptions, ſeemeth to ſport at the ſeueral edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Engliſh Bibles, in that there is no harmony or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent betweene them. The words may vary, but the ſenſe is one &amp; the ſame, and he whoſoeuer he be, forraine or domeſtique, that ſhall goe about to alter a knowen and receaued trueth, a white lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſhall marke his forehead, as we haue beene taught, ſo haue we beleeued, and he that addeth to this booke, God ſhall adde vnto him all the plagues conteined therein, and hee that taketh any thing away, God ſhal likewiſe race out his name out of the book of life, and giue vnto him his portion in the burning lake with hypocrites and foxes.</p>
            <p>No Prieſt may marry: diuerſe haue maintayned the ſame, ſo <hi>Alphonſus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irueſius aduerſus Lutheri dogmata</hi> affirmeth, and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rionius l.</hi> 2. <hi>topic: theolog:</hi> the Greeke Church haue allowed thereof. Our late Canoniſts haue founde out a newe deuiſe, that it is not lawfull for a Monk or a prieſt to marry openly, but priuatly <hi>mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri cum dispendio, aliud eſſe aiunt cum occulto Monachus duxit vxorem, quia tunc magis praeſumitur delo peccaſſe quam intellectus errore.</hi> So holdeth <hi>Francis Squilla de fide catholica cap.</hi> 15. &amp; <hi>Ludouicus Carer tractatu de haereticis numero</hi> 38. I could lay open ſeuerall repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all which will ſufficiently approue this, that in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there haue beene and are at this day to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſundry and diuers innouations. Let vs beloued, be firme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in the trueth, if any offer vnto vs any other doctrine ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſchiſme and diſſenſion refuſe the ſame, and as <hi>Baſil</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>aduerſus Anomaeos &amp; Sabillianos</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Chriſt himſelfe hath ſo taught vs: The Apoſtles of chriſt haue ſo preached <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the fathers in the primitiue church haue obſerued the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let it be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then for thee to ſay, I haue bene thus taught. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Saint Peter</hi> obſerueth two eſpeciall properties in them, the one is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their intemperancy: they ſhall be ſo licentious in their doctrine, that they care not what they ſpeake, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is their couetouſneſſe, they preach vnto you, ſaieth the Apoſtle not to ſaue your ſoules, but to ſaue themſelues to enrich themſelues, and theſe are two notable tokens to diſcerne a falſe teacher.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:15"/>
            <p>A riotous and luxurious perſon ouerthroweth himſelfe in his prodigality: ſo theſe riotous and luxurious preachers they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw themſelues in their ſuperfluities: he that in diputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath once made a breach into any abſurdity, he wil not ſpare to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low many: ſo theſe hauing erred in the principal points, of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion care not what they ſay. A foole ſaieth <hi>Salomon,</hi> he is lauiſh of his tongue, and hee that is vnaduiſed in his ſpeach ſhall feele miſchiefes. <hi>Dauid</hi> attributeth to a ſlaunderous tongue a fit reward, and that is hoat conſuming coales. <hi>Saint Iames</hi> in his third cap. A horſe, ſaith he, is an vnruly beaſt, if once he haue the bit in his mouth, will turne according to the will of the rider: a ſhip, a huge and vaſt veſſell is ruled in the ſea by a little peece of tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: the tongue is a little member, and it polluteth the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. There are few years in the which our phyſicians doe not giue out, that there is a new diſeaſe, inſomuch, they are ignorant how and in what order to proceede. This ſommer paſt, diuerſe haue beene infected with a dangerous malady tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their tongues haue had ſuch a ſhaking ague, that ſeldome they were at reſt: Hee ſaieth the Apoſtle, that offendeth not vvith his tongue, he is a perfect man. <hi>Homer</hi> obſerueth, that <hi>Irus</hi> the begger was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one that vſed no meaſure in ſpeaking, but in <hi>Menelaus</hi> he noteth this in him, that he vſed to ſpeake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, few words, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euery word weighed a pounde. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> in xlv. Sermon, <hi>ad fratres in eremo,</hi> deſcribeth ſundry inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences that haue happened vnto diuers by this exceſsiue ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot: <hi>videte fratres,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quanta mala habet lingua:</hi> brethren, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry are the inconueniences that the tongue bringeth. <hi>In bono magna eſt, in malo mors eſt,</hi> laudable in a good man, but preſent death it is in a wicked man. <hi>Diabolus vnde cecedit?</hi> Can you tel me how the diuell came by his fall: <hi>numquid adulterium fecit?</hi> aſſure your ſelues he committed no adultery: <hi>numquid furtum fecit,</hi> theft he neuer committed: <hi>diabolus non propter hoc cecidit,</hi> the diuill was not expelled out of heauen for theſe things: <hi>ſed propter linguam, cum dixit in caelum aſcendam ſuper ſydera, pona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thronum meum, &amp; ero altiſſimo:</hi> onely his tongue was in fault, when he ſaied, hee would aſcend vp into heauen, and place his ſeate aboue the ſtarres, and be equall to God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>In the Church of <hi>England</hi> there is but one vniforme conſent of praier, ratified by autority, yet that forme and order of praier,
<pb facs="tcp:25165:16"/> cannot by no meanes be receaued. For we wil pray as we are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. This mans praier is effectuall, it conteineth in it, all things that are requiſite to corporall ſuſtenance, or ſpirituall comfort. The prayer preſcribed in the Church by authority, they are thankeſgiuings for victories obteyned by <hi>Dauid,</hi> or elſe if of late yeares they haue beene ſet downe, they doe not concerne the ſtate of the preſent time. Againe, diuerſe are ſo addicted to their own fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies, that if it be not adorned with variety of choiſe words, and beautified with metaphors, contayning ſundry and diuerſe repetitions, they doe not regarde the ſame. Our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the Church is to praiſe God, with one vniforme conſent of praier, one man he hath writen praiers, and ſo he praieth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Another, he deuiſeth a praier as he kneeleth, if the preacher be not as they require, they will not repaire to heare him. One man he comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the order of praiers, preſcribed by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> another alloweth not ſo well of that, as he doeth of certaine praiers that were priuily prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of late yeares: in fine, ſo they may deface the vniforme order of praier, in the booke of common prayer they could bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to receaue any order whatſoeuer.<note place="margin">John Penry his vnlerned confutation of Master D. Ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>croftes ſermon.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn Penrie</hi> hath of late ſet forth a paltry pamphlet, carying a ſhew of a confutation of a learned Sermon, preached out of this place, by a learned and a reuerende man, wherein hee inueigheth againſt notable and learned pointes of doctrine, the which the poore ſeely ſoule doeth not vnderſtand. And to aggrauate the matter, hee deſireth them vnto whoſe hands his booke ſhall come, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the Collect appointed for <hi>Saint Michaell</hi> the Archangell, wherein he ſaieth, there is plainly ſet downe a plaine article, of popery, praier to Saints. On the other ſide, I deſire you, that at this day heare me, at your comming home to peruſe the collect, if you can finde any one ſuch point therein conteyned, tending to his wordes. I will recant this that I ſay, if not, I beſeech you for Gods cauſe ſuſpect theſe men, that ſeeke nothing but the ouerthrow of Religion, and the ſubuerſion of the ſtate, yet all is not they would haue it, you haue gotten the ſtart of vs. Our bookes are forbidden, our printing preſſes are taken from vs, and our prolocutor. <hi>T. C.</hi> is now in durance. <hi>Libanius</hi> the Sophiſt, made a Rhetoricall declamation, adorned with tropes, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with variety of ſentences, and the phraſe of it ſelfe ſo
<pb facs="tcp:25165:16"/> fluent and copious that <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate peruſing the ſame, cried out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Libanius</hi> ſaieth he, thou art <hi>aureus partus matris tuae.</hi> I neuer heard of the like: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, O the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of thy declamation <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what an inuincible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument haſt thou, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I haue not ſeene ſo elegant a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo forth. So theſe men <hi>T. C.</hi> hath ouerthrown them by the word of God, if his tongue and pen were at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he is now better furniſhed then euer he was. The preſbytery of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be furniſhed with ſufficient preachers, all ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals remoued, the gouernement of the Church ſhould peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be gouerned, and the ſpirit of prophecy ſhould not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. Well I am aſſured of one thing, I ſhall haue no thankes for my labour, and I looke for none, what I haue ſpoken is for the duty that I owe to the Church of God, and to benefit the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle would haue vs to pray continually, lifting vp pure handes vnto heauen, and as long as we heape one innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon the necke of another, ſo long we exceed in exceſſiue riot and blaſpheme the way of truth. The ſecond thing that the Apoſtle obſerueth in theſe falſe teachers is, their couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a fault not tolerable in them that are appointed by God to inſtruct his people. This vice it is too too common among vs. Our liuings are pared and little is reſerued for vs, patrones ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be content to keepe them in their owne hands, or if they cannot he that is preſented vnto it, of neceſsity he muſt offer ſomewhat to the ſiluer ſhrine of <hi>Simon</hi> before his inſtitution. Others againe that haue ſufficient, they prouide for others, &amp; heap vp riches for their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In the meane ſeaſon, open exclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded forth derogatory to the church &amp; her miniſters. <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> writing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 143. <hi>Pſa. Videtis</hi> ſaith he, <hi>magiſtros haereticorum nihil aliud fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere niſi ſtudere diuitijs: diuitijs ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; paupere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nunt,</hi> it is the cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of falſe teachers to heap vp riches in making greater accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this world, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they doe of Chriſt. Couetouſnes, it hath ouerthrowen multitudes, it is the root of al miſchiefe, <hi>vnde habeas, quaerit nemo, ſed oportet habere,</hi> ſo we haue it, we care not how, &amp; in what order we come by it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Bern.</hi> in a treatiſe that he writeth <hi>de bonis deſere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis</hi> deciphereth the eſtate of his time. A gentleman ſaith hee hath 4. children. This ſay they ſhall haue an aduouſion of ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent perſonage,
<pb facs="tcp:25165:17"/> the other ſhall attend vpon my Lord Biſhop, <hi>vt ditetur de bonis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ne in noſtros liberos noſtra diuidatur haereditas.</hi> This ſhall attend in the Vniuerſity vpon ſome one man that ſhall be heade of an houſe. And in time it may ſo fall out, that <hi>in delicijs &amp; delictis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritus Archidia conatu dignus habeatur,</hi> he ſhall be a fit man to bee an Archdeacon. Another, that by reaſon of his pouerty hath no frends, <hi>vndi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſedulus circuit,</hi> rangeth vp and downe the country: <hi>obſequitur blanditur, ſimulat &amp; diſſimulat,</hi> with cap and knee he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth on his patrone, if at the laſt he may intrude himſelfe <hi>in patrimonium crucifixi &amp; bona domini,</hi> vpon the goods of the Church: <hi>quae ſola ex omnibus hodie inueniuntur expoſita,</hi> the which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone at this day are laied open for euery one, in the meane ſeaſon he vnto whom theſe goods appertaine which is Chriſt, <hi>peregre profectus eſt,</hi> hee is gone abroade, <hi>in plenilunio rediturus,</hi> at the full moone he purpoſeth to returne: and of all theſe he will ſeuerely exact his own. If any think that I haue gone further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhould, he is deceaued,<note place="margin">Bernard de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is deſerendis.</note> theſe words are not mine but <hi>Bernards.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> he pointeth at theſe teachers and telleth vs: <hi>quae ſua ſunt quaerentes non quae Ieſu Chriſti,</hi> they ſeeke thoſe things that concerne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and not thoſe things which concerne the honour of god. Such a one was <hi>Nicholas</hi> one of the ſeuen deacons: and <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> if he could haue purchaſed the holy Ghoſt with his money, he would not haue bene a loſer. Liuings of the Church are ſale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ware in theſe daies, ſundry intrude themſelues into liuinges, of the which they are vnworthy. <hi>Giez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the 4. <hi>Reg. c.</hi> 5. for his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was ſtricken with a leproſie. <hi>Iudas</hi> in ſelling our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption hanged himſelfe. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> for his voluntary proffer, hee was vtterly reiected by S. <hi>Peter Act.</hi> 8. Chriſt he draue away theſe money changers out of his temple.</p>
            <p>Men ſo that they may obtain riches what waies they vſe they care not. Church lands are not greatly ſought for: but if they lie in their way, they can eaſily be intreated to take them. Our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtores, thought it works of charity to builde Churches, &amp; their progeny vpon a zeale, pull downe Churches <hi>eccleſias Chriſti quas fundauere parentes, perdere nitunturnati pietate carentes.</hi> I will leaue this, and haſten to the thirde and laſt part of my diuiſion. Let vs beloued, liue together in Chriſtian vnity, verily ſaieth Chriſt, if you loue one another then are you my Diſciples, let vs auoide al exceſſe whatſoeuer, and euery one labour to maintain the truth, for</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25165:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
